4

My struggle with Depression

My mind goes back to the years after World War II. I had served four and a half years with the British forces in the Middle East. Then, at the time of my discharge, I married Lydia Christensen, a Danish schoolteacher who was head of a small children’s home in Jerusalem. Through my marriage to Lydia, I became father of a ready-made family of eight girls, of whom six were Jewish, one was a Palestinian Arab and the youngest was English.

Together as a family we witnessed the rebirth of the State of Israel in 1948, and then moved to London. We found a city still struggling wearily to rebuild its life from the shattering impact of the war. Night after night the Nazi bombers had rained down terror and destruction on a population that had no way to retaliate. Long after the bombs had ceased to fall, the raw scars were still visible throughout the city.

Many of the streets reminded me of a person trying to smile with two or three front teeth knocked out. In the midst of the rows of houses that remained standing, vacant, weed-filled lots served as a wordless memorial to whole families that had perished with their homes. Uglier still were vacant shells of houses that remained standing but with blackened, crumbling walls and boarded windows. The eye searched in vain for any remnant of elegance or beauty.

The external scars of the city were matched by the emotional scars the people bore within themselves. The prevailing mood was one of weary cynicism. Britain had emerged victorious from the war, but the fruits of victory were bitter. All but the most basic forms of food were scarce. Such commodities as sugar, butter, tea and tobacco, which might have made life just a little easier to enjoy – or at least to endure – were still strictly rationed. Queues were long, tempers frayed.

The level of spiritual life in Britain was lower than it had been for at least two hundred years. Fewer than five percent of the population regularly attended any place of worship. Many churches had been either boarded up or converted into furniture storehouses. Of the churches that remained open, few presented any positive message of hope that could serve as an antidote to the prevailing depression.

Shortly after we settled in London, I began pastoring a small Pentecostal congregation near the centre of the city.

My prevailing impression of that time is one of greyness. The streets were grey, the houses were grey, the people were grey. Most of the time the skies, too, were grey. The fuel being used for heating at the time blocked at least 25 percent of the sunlight that would have helped to relieve the greyness. In winter the city was shrouded from time to time by fog so dense you could not see your own hand stretched out in front of you.

Yet there was another kind of greyness that was even more depressing. It was the strange, indefinable greyness inside my own soul. By the spiritual standards of the time, I was a relatively successful minister. Each week a person would come to the Lord or I would witness a miracle of healing or some other demonstration of the supernatural power of the Holy Spirit. Yet I had a continuous inner sense of frustration. An inaudible voice seemed to whisper, Others may succeed, but you won’t.

My experience up to this time had been a series of successes. Elected as a King’s Scholar at Eton at age thirteen, I had gone on to King’s College, Cambridge, as the senior scholar of my year. After graduating with first-class honours in both parts of the Classical Tripos (the official course of study in the Latin and Greek languages, culture and history), I had then been selected as the senior research student of the university for two years. Finally, at age 24, I had been elected to a coveted position as a Fellow of King’s College, Cambridge. During the war my service with the Medical Corps in a non-combatant role had barred me from promotion to officer rank. Nevertheless I had emerged with the highest character qualification that the British Army had to bestow: exemplary.

During my military service I experienced a supernatural encounter with Jesus Christ that revolutionised my goals in life. Since my discharge I could see how God had led me step by step to my present ministry as a pastor. This was the irony I could not resolve. While I had been making my own way through life, ignoring God, I had an unbroken record of success. Yet now, as I was sincerely seeking to follow God’s plan for my life, I was oppressed by the continuing sense that I could never expect to succeed.

In all of this I never doubted the reality of my salvation. It was too deep and too permanent. Yet at times depression descended on me like a grey mist that shrouded my head and shoulders. Breaking out of this mist was like attempting to break out of a prison. I felt isolated and lonely, shut off from meaningful communication, even with those closest to me – my wife and daughters. I did not know any mature minister to whom I could turn for help.

I tried every spiritual means I knew to throw off this depression. I read my Bible faithfully at least twice a day. I fasted one day each week. At times I devoted several days or a week to intensive prayer and fasting. At such times the depression lifted for a while, but inevitably it returned. Each time it did, my hopelessness grew deeper.

I was familiar with Romans 6:11, which instructs us to “reckon [ourselves] to be dead indeed unto sin” (kjv). Day after day I reckoned myself dead to sin and to any consequence of depression that it had brought on me. But I could not seem to experience the latter half of the verse: being “alive unto God through Jesus Christ” (kjv).

Overcoming My Enemy

Finally in 1953, when I had exhausted all my own resources, God came to my help in a way I had never contemplated. I was reading the opening verses of Isaiah 61, which describe the supernatural work of the Holy Spirit in bearing testimony to the message of the Gospel – verses Jesus applied to Himself in the synagogue in Nazareth (see Luke 4:16-21). As I came to the words in verse 3, “the garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness” (kjv, emphasis added) – also called “a spirit of despair” (niv) and “a spirit of fainting” (nasb) – I could read no further. It was as though the phrase the spirit of heaviness was underlined by some invisible hand.

I repeated the phrase to myself: the spirit of heaviness. Was this God’s diagnosis of my condition? Could it mean that the force I was struggling with was not part of myself, but an alien person – an evil spirit being that somehow occupied an area of my mind?

I recalled a term I had once heard but did not understand: familiar spirit. Did it possibly refer to some kind of evil power that attached itself to the members of a family, moving down from generation to generation?

I thought about an aspect of my father’s character that had always puzzled me. He was a good, moral man and a successful officer who had retired from the Army with the rank of colonel. For 98 percent of the time he behaved like the English gentleman he was. But during the fractional two percent of the time, I had seen something in him quite alien to his own personality. Some apparently trivial incident would upset him and, for as long as 24 hours, he would lapse into rigid, stony silence. He would shut himself off from my mother and would not open his mouth even to say thank you for a cup of tea. Then, with no apparent reason, he would return to his normal, well-mannered self.

With this new insight, I saw that a similar “dark spirit” had followed me through my life, from childhood onward. Apparently it had studied my temperament and was familiar with my weaknesses and my reactions. It knew just when I would be most vulnerable to its pressures. It now had one main objective: to prevent me from serving Christ effectively.

This was a decisive moment in my life. I had always regarded my depression and negative attitude as an expression of my own character – something I had been born with. I had felt guilty that I was not a “better” Christian. Now it became clear to me that my struggle was not against part of my own personality at all.

Immediately the Holy Spirit brought to my mind the promise of Joel 2:32: “And it shall come to pass, that whosoever shall call on the name of the Lord shall be delivered” (kjv). From my study of Hebrew, I knew this verb also means “to save, to rescue.” I determined to apply this promise and to act on it. I said a simple prayer that went something like this: “Lord, You’ve shown me that I have been oppressed by a spirit of heaviness, but You have promised in Your Word that if I call on Your name, I shall be delivered. So I’m calling on You now to deliver me, in the name of Jesus!”

The response was immediate. Something like a huge, heavenly vacuum cleaner came down over me and sucked away the grey mist that shrouded my head and shoulders. At the same time a pressure in the area of my chest was forcibly released, and I gave a little gasp.

God had answered my prayer. Suddenly everything around me seemed brighter. I felt as if a heavy burden had been lifted from my shoulders. I was free! All my life I had been under that oppression. It felt strange to be free. But I discovered quickly that freedom was normal and that oppression was abnormal.

My old enemy did not give up on me; I still had to struggle against depression. But the great difference now was that its attacks came from without, not from within. I gradually learned how to withstand it.

The main thrust of the attacks was to induce in me reactions or attitudes of pessimism. When everything seemed to be going wrong, I would begin to entertain negative thoughts about what I could expect to happen. Quite soon I would feel the all-too-familiar grey mist beginning to settle down over my head and shoulders.

At this point God taught me another important lesson: He would do for me what I could not do for myself, but He would not do for me what He required me to do for myself. God had responded to my cry and delivered me from the spirit of heaviness, but after that He held me responsible to exercise scriptural discipline over my own thoughts.

Clearly I needed something to protect my mind. As I meditated on Paul’s list of spiritual armour in Ephesians 6:13-18, I concluded that what Paul calls “the helmet of salvation” was provided for the protection of my mind. This left me wondering, Do I already have the helmet of salvation? I know I’m saved. Does that mean I have the helmet automatically?

Then I saw that Paul was writing to Christians who were already saved, but he still instructed them to “take” the helmet of salvation. This placed the responsibility on me. I had to “take” the helmet for myself. But what was the helmet?

Fortunately I was using a Bible with cross references. The cross reference to Ephesians 6:17 was 1 Thessalonians 5:8: “Putting on . . . for an helmet, the hope of salvation” (kjv). So the helmet God had provided to protect my mind was hope!

This appealed to my logical mind. My problem was pessimism, but the opposite of pessimism is optimism – hoping continually for the best. Hope, therefore, was my protection.

From 1 Thessalonians 5:8 I was led to Hebrews 6:18-20:

That . . . we might have a strong consolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope set before us: which hope we have as an anchor of the soul, both sure and steadfast, and which entereth into that within the veil; whither the forerunner is for us entered, even Jesus. . . .

(kjv)

I found here two further pictures of hope. First, hope is compared to the horns of the altar. Under the old covenant, when a man was being pursued by an enemy seeking to kill him, he could find asylum by clinging to the horns of the altar, where his enemy could not reach him. For me the altar spoke of the sacrifice Jesus made for me on the cross. Its horns represented my hope, which was based on His sacrifice. As long as I clung tenaciously to this hope, my enemy could not approach to destroy me.

What about the second picture of hope, as an anchor? This provoked a brief dialogue in my mind.

What needs an anchor?

A ship.

Why does a ship need an anchor?

Because it floats in water – an unstable element that provides nothing for it to hold onto. It passes its anchor through that unstable element, therefore, and fastens it onto something firm and immovable, such as a rock.

I saw that hope could be like that in my life – an anchor passing through the turmoil and instability of this life and fastened forever onto the eternal Rock of Ages – Jesus.

As I meditated on this, however, I realised there is a difference between hope and wishful thinking. Reading on in Hebrews, I saw that “faith is the substance of things hoped for” (Hebrews 11:1, kjv). The kind of hope I needed as an anchor had to be based on a solid foundation of faith in the statements and promises of God’s Word. Without this biblical foundation, hope could prove to be nothing but wishful thinking.

Gradually I worked out a simple, practical way to apply these truths in my daily life. I learned to distinguish between thoughts that proceeded from my own mind and those insinuated by the demon. Every time my enemy approached me and sought to induce negative and pessimistic thoughts, I disciplined myself to counter with a positive word from Scripture.

If the demon suggested that things were going wrong, I would counter with Romans 8:28: “All things work together for good to those who love God, to those who are the called according to His purpose.” I love God, I would answer my invisible enemy, and I am called according to His purpose. Therefore, all these things are working together for my good.

From time to time the demon would resort to the tactic it had often used successfully in the past: You’ll never succeed. I would counter this with Philippians 4:13: “I can do all things through Christ who strengthens me.”

Complete victory did not come immediately. But over the course of time, my mental reflexes were built up to the point that it was almost automatic to counter any negative suggestion from the demon with some opposite, positive word from Scripture. As a result, that particular demon seldom wastes much time now in attacking me.

God also began to teach me the importance of thanking and praising Him continually. This would surround me, I discovered, with an atmosphere that repelled demons. I was impressed by the words of David in Psalm 34:1: “I will bless the Lord at all times; His praise shall continually be in my mouth.”

The introduction to this psalm indicates that at this point in David’s life he was a fugitive from King Saul, who was seeking to kill him. He had escaped to the court of a Gentile king (Abimelech or Achish), who did not give him a warm welcome. To save his life David “feigned madness in their hands, scratched on the doors of the gate, and let his saliva fall down on his beard” (1 Samuel 21:13).

If David could continue blessing God in that situation, I reasoned, there is no situation in which I should not be doing the same.

Lessons

Out of all these struggles, I learned three lessons that have ever since proven invaluable: first, the reality of demonic activity as described in the New Testament; second, the supernatural provision God has made for deliverance; and third, the need to maintain deliverance by the disciplined application of Scripture.

Christians often tend to be one-sided in their approach to the issue of deliverance. Some place all their emphasis on the actual process of expelling a demon. Others reject the supernatural element in deliverance and stress only the need for Christian discipline.

The truth is that neither is a substitute for the other. Deliverance cannot take the place of discipline, and discipline cannot take the place of deliverance. Both are needed.

Looking back over the years, I have asked myself from time to time, What course would my life have taken if God had not come to my help with His supernatural power and delivered me from that evil “spirit of heaviness”? I have no doubt that sooner or later I would have given way to despair and been forced out of the ministry. How wonderful, therefore, to look back on the more than forty years of fruitful ministry that have followed my deliverance!

I realise, however, that my struggle with demons was not a strange or unique experience. On the contrary, those called into Christian ministry are, I believe, among Satan’s prime targets. He subjects them to relentless demonic pressure and torment, aiming to force them out of their ministry. All too often he is successful!

There is only one sure protection: learning how to recognise demonic activity and deal with it according to the pattern established by Jesus.

That is one main reason I feel constrained to write this book.

15

Is Witchcraft Still at Work Today?

As we trace the tortuous, deceptive paths of demonic activity and the occult, we discover that they all proceed from one primal source: witchcraft.

Witchcraft is the universal, primeval religion of fallen humanity. When the human race turned from God in rebellion, the power that moved in was witchcraft. As the Bible says, “Rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft” (1 Samuel 15:23). Each people group practices its own distinctive form of witchcraft, but certain elements are common to almost all of them.

In many parts of the world, the open practice of witchcraft has continued unchanged for centuries. In nations with a Christian history, primarily in the West, witchcraft has adapted itself to the culture and takes certain special forms. Previously confined to a small minority, in these last decades it has become continually more blatant and aggressive.

The supernatural element in witchcraft fascinates many people in our contemporary, materialistic Western culture. Where people are familiar only with a form of religion (whether church or synagogue) that operates solely on a material and intellectual plane, they are prone to look for an alternative that offers the supernatural, particularly if it offers power. This is why multitudes of such people are now turning to some form of witchcraft.

One purpose common to all forms of witchcraft is control. Whenever any religious activity seeks to control other people, the influence of witchcraft is probably at work. Some reading this chapter know exactly what I am talking about because they have escaped from Satan’s clutches. Others will grasp at this opportunity to find their way out. Still others will utilise this information to help set people free.

The primitive practice of witchcraft normally contains the following elements: a priesthood (witch doctor, medicine man, shaman); a ritual or liturgy (which may take various forms); a sacrifice (animal or human); some characteristic form of music (often incantation or drumbeats); and some form of covenant binding the participants to one another and to whatever satanic being is the focus of their activity. The word coven (a gathering of witches) is probably derived from the same root as covenant.

These are the four main aims of witchcraft:

To propitiate a higher spiritual being, often regarded as capricious or malevolent
To control the forces of nature, such as rain or good weather for harvest
To ward off sickness and infertility, as in Africa, where almost every barren woman will go to the witch doctor for a potion or charm
To control other human beings – to terrify enemies in battle or to produce sexual desire in one person toward another

Four Levels of Modern Witchcraft

The Westernised, “modern” practice of witchcraft contains the same elements. It operates on at least four levels:

Open, public, “respectable”
“Underground” – covens
Fifth column, disguised within society and the Church
A work of the flesh

1. Open, Public, “Respectable”

Operating in its real nature, witchcraft teaches and practices the worship of Satan. The Church of Satan has its own web site on the Internet, which presents it as a “respectable” church. But those who have come out of its clutches will tell you that the central satanic ceremony is a “black mass” – a blasphemous parody of a Christian Communion service. The dominant motivation is a deliberate, conscious hatred and rejection of Jesus Christ. The main enemy is the Christian Church.

2. “Underground” – Covens

Witchcraft covens usually meet at night to offer sacrifices and to initiate new members. One central element in the practice of witchcraft (as we saw in the testimony at the end of the last chapter) is sacrifice. Usually the sacrifices are animal – a dog, cat, rat or some other small animal. According to my understanding, however, the sacrifice is, whenever possible, human, usually a baby. There are also reported incidents of young people being required to kill and even behead victims as part of their initiation into witchcraft.

The “god” of witchcraft is Satan. Its adherents are bound to him and to one another by a covenant committing them to absolute secrecy concerning their activities.

What attracts people to Satanism? I believe it is the offer of supernatural power. Once convinced of the power they have acquired, Satanists are often bold and aggressive.

A Christian friend of mine was sitting on an aeroplane next to a woman who refused all the food that was served. The woman told my friend she was fasting and praying.

“I’m a Christian, too,” my friend said, “and sometimes I fast and pray.”

“Oh, no!” the woman replied. “I’m not a Christian, I’m a Satanist.” She went on to explain that she had two main objectives in her prayer: the break-up of Christian marriages and the downfall of leading Christian ministers.

Statistics released in recent decades must surely have encouraged her to believe that her prayers were very effective.

I once received a pathetic letter from a woman in Texas who listened regularly to my radio broadcast. She was a witch, she said, and had been assigned to a certain church to plant doubt and unbelief in the hearts and minds of new or weak Christians. She had succeeded in drawing away three such people. Then she wrote, “Do you believe I can be forgiven and receive salvation from Jesus?” I replied that God is infinitely merciful, even though it might be a struggle for her to be totally free, and I directed her to a local pastor.

3. Fifth Column, Disguised

I will not attempt to present all the forms taken by witchcraft to entice innocent people into the worship of Satan. I will merely offer some examples.

Rock Music

Rock music is one of the main channels, and its potential for harm is fearsome. Here is a letter I received recently from a 33-year-old man. (A member of my staff responded and sought to help him.) I obtained permission to quote it:

Dear Mr. Prince,

I am writing to you today to tell you of my struggles with demonization. I know what I write probably won’t be new for you, but to friends, family and church leaders, I must look like a psychopath.

It all started when I was sixteen and started listening to one of my brother’s rock albums. This was not just any rock album, but a very demonic album. The album was by Black Sabbath, and the cover had 666 on the top with a demonic-looking creature peering at you. On the inside of the album was a picture of a man in bed with several demons (at least six or seven) around him as if to pounce on him. The look on the man’s face was pure agony. I only listened to it once or twice, but that was too many.

One day I heard a very peculiar noise coming from the stereo cabinet. When I bent over to reach for the doors, a force went in me or through me and pushed me back. This was a very distinct force, and I am sure that demons were involved. I had a thought that I should hide the album so no one could throw it away – surely this was from the demons. To this day I can’t remember where I hid it, even though I pray for remembrance.

Well, ever since then my life has been a living hell. These demons hold me down and paralyse me when I start to fall asleep. I can’t move, speak or open my eyes. All I can do is cry out mentally for Jesus to help me. These demons are vicious; they rape me in every way imaginable. (I could get graphic and give a more detailed account, but I don’t think that would be appropriate at this time.) This was an every-night ordeal for me from the time I was sixteen until I was 31. The sexual abuse started to subside when I started attending Bible study and church regularly.

Now, I know what you’re probably thinking: “Are you saved, and is Jesus Lord of your life?” I said the Lord’s Prayer when I was twelve with my mother at my side and have said it hundreds of times since then. This is due mainly to the fact that Christian friends, and everyone in any of the churches and Bible studies I’ve been to, tell me this can’t happen to a Christian. So, you see, I’m waiting for signs of my salvation by the evidence of my life getting back to normal. It is hard to believe or have faith when you are bombarded with so many conflicting reports. I can’t even think straight anymore, or hold down a job for more than six to twelve months. I’m not stupid; I earned an engineering degree. I’m just confused.

I come from a so-called Christian family; both my parents are born again, along with one of my two sisters. My only brother is not. My parents are supporters of your ministry but I don’t think they believe in demonization of people. I think this is because every time I bring it up, my father will weakly and timidly tell me to rebuke it in the name of Jesus and turn and walk away. My mother, on the other hand, refuses to acknowledge it and has even told my sister to stop discussing it with me. My mother’s side of the family has a potential demonic nature; her father (dead) was a Freemason and her mother (also dead) and two surviving sisters (living) out of three are involved with Eastern Star.

I know this letter sounds really crazy, but I hope it makes a little sense to you, and I wish I could tell you more, but that would mean writing a book.

Isn’t this tragic? A professing Christian is tormented by demons but receives no understanding, much less help, from fellow Christians. (I mentioned the danger of Freemasonry and its women’s affiliate, Eastern Star, in chapter 12.)

Obviously the young man was foolish to expose himself to forces so obviously satanic. But others are exposed to similar satanic forces in less obvious forms. The combined elements at a rock concert or discotheque, for example, also open the way for demons: deafening music with an insistent, repetitive beat; lyrics that range from mindless to blasphemous; strobe lights constantly fluctuating in colour and intensity. The impact can break down a person’s ability to reason or exercise moral judgement, and thus open the way for demons, especially if alcohol or drugs are involved.

New Age Cults, Religions and Practices

The fifth column operation of witchcraft is continually expanding. One major “front” is the strange assortment of cults, religions and philosophies grouped loosely under the banner of the New Age. Unfortunately, many who sincerely think of themselves as Christians are being drawn in by its seductive promises and deceptive terminology. Some who desire to stay healthy and fit, for example, do not realise that many health food stores are permeated with New Age products and teaching materials.

Likewise, many people are drawn into the occult and opened up to demonic forces through hypnosis. Some people are intrigued by hypnosis as “innocent” entertainment, perhaps on TV. Others come under Satan’s power through a medical practitioner, for treatment of psychiatric problems or as a form of “anesthesia” for surgical procedures.3

Another occult practice that opens the door to demons is acupuncture. Some physicians and other medical personnel today justify its use on the ground that “it works!” But an analysis of its occult background reveals that acupuncture will never ultimately promote the well-being of those who submit to it.

The following warning comes from a Chinese doctor in Malaysia:

About eight years ago, at a retreat in Singapore, God spoke to me about the dangers of acupuncture and its link to the occult, especially its inseparable origin with traditional Chinese religion. I immediately renounced my practice of acupuncture – a skill I learned in Hong Kong and practised successfully for five years.

As soon as I came back home, I announced to my startled staff of doctors, nurses and patients that acupuncture is dangerous and that I had renounced it and would not practice it anymore. I gathered all my machines, needles, books, diploma and charts and made a great bonfire of them publicly. The total cost of the items was about $15,000 – but the blessings after that were priceless because:

1. My wife, who had suffered from chronic migraine and had acupuncture, done by me many times before, was immediately healed without medicine or prayer.

2. My unexplained fear of darkness immediately vanished.

3. My medical practice, instead of suffering a loss, received a double-fold increase in blessings.

About three years ago we saw a very unusual case during a healing rally in Kuching, East Malaysia. A Christian lady came forward for prayer regarding her rheumatism. As soon as we started, the Lord gave a word of knowledge that she had submitted herself to acupuncture treatment in the past. She confirmed it, but each time she tried to renounce it, she was thrown onto the floor screaming in severe pain.

We realised that she was being tormented by demons that had gained entry to her body through acupuncture. After we took authority over the demons and cast them out in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, she was delivered and totally healed. She then told us that each time she had tried to renounce acupuncture, invisible needles began to pierce her over the parts of her body where she had previously submitted herself to treatment.

Let me end by relating a tragic case. The Christian brother who taught me acupuncture suffered from severe depression and committed suicide under mysterious circumstances. The world does not know the whole truth, because he had everything in life, but I think I know: He came under a curse and paid for it with his life.

4. A Work of the Flesh (“Sinful Nature,” NIV)

Now that we have examined three main forms of witchcraft as a supernatural force (the open, public form; the underground form; and the fifth column), we must expose the root. It is the least recognised operation, but it permeates society and the Church.

In Galatians 5:19-21 Paul lists the works of the “flesh” (“sinful nature,” niv). In the middle he mentions “idolatry, sorcery” (nkjv) or “idolatry and witchcraft” (niv). As I said at the beginning of this chapter, the root of witchcraft lies in our flesh – our fallen, rebellious, sinful nature.

This nature often manifests itself, even in infancy, in efforts to control other people. We feel secure if we can control others. Then they do not threaten us; they do what we want. God, on the other hand, never seeks to control us. He respects the free will He has given each of us, although He does hold us responsible for how we use that freedom.

There are three ways the desire to control others expresses itself: manipulation, intimidation and domination. The goal is domination. People who recognise that they are weaker than those they seek to control tend to manipulate; those who feel stronger tend to intimidate. But the end purpose is the same: to dominate – that is, to control others and get them to do what we want.

Many family relationships portray this. Husbands intimidate their wives by fits of rage or actual violence. Wives manipulate their husbands by tears and hurt feelings, and often by making them feel guilty for their shortcomings. Parents frequently intimidate or manipulate their children. But, alternatively, children can become extremely adept at manipulating their parents.

One main tool of manipulation is guilt. A mother may say to her son, “Honey, if you love Mother, you’ll run to the store and get me a pack of cigarettes.” How does that affect the child? He is made to feel guilty if he does not do what Mother asks. It will be taken as a sign that he does not love her. That is not a fair way to treat a child.

Alternatively, however, a child may manipulate his mother. When she is entertaining guests, he comes and asks to watch a forbidden TV programme. He knows Mother is very careful to protect him from harmful influences, but he calculates that she will not risk his tantrum by refusing him in front of her guests.

Once we learn to recognise the desire to control others as an evil, manipulative force, we will see it at work in many different areas.

In religion it may be in the way a preacher appeals for an offering: “God has shown me that there are ten people here tonight who will each give a thousand dollars.” Or he shows tear-jerking pictures of starving children in a distant land, and anyone who does not respond is made to feel guilty: Perhaps I am one of those ten people or If I don’t give something for those children, I must be a heartless person.

In politics it may be in the way a candidate subtly appeals to racial prejudice in order to win votes. In business it is often expressed in advertising that entices people to want what they do not need and to buy what they cannot afford. In every case it is evil.

Once we recognise these devices as disguises of witchcraft, we realise that in our contemporary culture we are being exposed continually to its pressure. This gives new meaning to Paul’s statement in 2 Corinthians 4:4 that “the god of this age has blinded the minds of unbelievers” (niv).

Repeated yielding to any fleshly lust can open the way for a corresponding demon to enter. This applies to all the works of the flesh listed in Galatians 5:19-21. A person who yields regularly to fornication or jealousy or envy (to name but three) will probably be taken over by the corresponding demon.

This applies no less to witchcraft. People who habitually use manipulation or intimidation to control others will be taken over by a demon of witchcraft. After that they will be unable to relate to anyone apart from these tactics. Now it will be no longer just the flesh at work, but a new, supernatural power that can bring the person(s) they control into a condition of spiritual slavery.

I have seen this demonic power at work between mother and daughter. A mother may decide that her daughter should marry a man from a certain racial background or social level. Then, if the man the daughter chooses does not meet the mother’s criteria, the spirit of witchcraft in the mother will cause her to react in such a way that she actually puts a curse on her daughter and prospective son-in-law. The curse may take a verbal form: “If you marry that man, you’ll never have enough. He’ll never provide for you.” As a result, the couple will find themselves struggling continually against pressures and frustrations for which they can find no obvious cause.

The demon of witchcraft can also work in many other kinds of relationships. Sometimes a pastor seeks to control the members of his staff or even his whole congregation. Or a business executive may intimidate his subordinates. Or a political leader diverts the attention of his people from their own desperate need by stirring up hatred against some “enemy” nation.

Whenever this kind of controlling relationship exists between two people, the person being controlled almost invariably needs deliverance from witchcraft. Likewise, the person exercising control needs deliverance. But each person must meet the conditions for being delivered. On one side, the person exercising control must repent and renounce his or her desire to control. On the other side, the person being controlled must repent of submitting to such control and must sever the binding relationship.

The Way Out

In chapter 21 I will give thorough teaching on how to be set free, but let me say at this point that people who have participated in satanic worship and have exercised the power Satan gave them must be very determined (as I told the woman from Texas) if they are to be set free. The spiritual struggle will probably be intense.

Lydia and I were once part of a small group ministering to a young woman who told us she had been a priestess of Satan but had repented and longed to be free. At one point she showed us her ring symbolising her marriage to Satan. At our urging she finally removed it – but then the demon compelled her to swallow it! One of our workers, a young man, received a supernatural anointing of faith and commanded the woman to regurgitate the ring, which she promptly did. The young man then picked up the ring and threw it into a nearby lake.

The young woman’s deliverance was consummated when she made a public confession to a group of Christians and burned every garment she had ever worn while worshipping Satan. This was in line with the biblical exhortation to “[hate] even the garment defiled by the flesh” (Jude 23).

The actual experience of deliverance, however, is not the end of the conflict. A person who has made a conscious, unreserved commitment to Satan is still regarded by him as his property, held by him in eternal bondage. He will seek continually to re-establish his control, using every kind of demon under his command.

So Satan’s former victim will need the help of a committed company of believers to stand with him. He needs to learn to resist every pressure, continually affirming and reaffirming the Scriptures that guarantee deliverance and victory. In this Jesus Himself is our example. Each time He was approached by Satan with a temptation, He countered with one, all-sufficient response: “It is written . . .” (Matthew 4:1-11). Satan has no answer to the written Word of God.

In the wisdom of God, this process of continually resisting every demonic pressure serves a positive purpose. When a person has been enslaved by Satan, the inner walls of his or her personality have been broken down. After deliverance, in order to retain freedom, the protecting walls must be rebuilt. The continuously repeated assertion of appropriate Scriptures gradually rebuilds the walls. Once they are firmly in place, the satanic pressures will gradually diminish and eventually cease. Satan is too clever to send his troops into a battle he knows he can no longer win.

How can people protect themselves from deception? There is only one door (as I explained in the previous chapter) that leads into the Kingdom of God: Jesus, who is “the way, the truth, and the life” (John 14:6). Those who enter the realm of the supernatural through any other door find themselves in the kingdom of darkness, not of light.

We must be on our guard, as I will explain in chapter 16, that we are not deceived into following “another Jesus” – one who does not correspond with the Jesus portrayed in the Bible and who will not lead us into the truth.

There is also only one absolute standard of truth. In John 17:17 Jesus says to the Father, “Your word is truth.” Anything that does not harmonise with the Bible is error. For this reason it is important that we study the basic truths and principles of the Bible, so that we are always ready to apply this test to anything that claims our credence. But again, we must be on our guard. Not everyone who glibly quotes the Scripture practices obedience to it. (See my booklet Protection from Deception.)

Now let us proceed to the sixth commonly asked question concerning the realm of the demonic.

3. In late 1997 more than 700 people, mostly school children, were taken to hospital with convulsions triggered by watching an animated cartoon on television. According to Reuters, “The blame was put on a scene depicting an explosion followed by five seconds of flashing red lights from the eyes of ‘Pikachu,’ a rat-like creature. . . . Children went into a trance-like state, similar to hypnosis, complaining of shortness of breath, nausea, and bad vision when the rat-like creature’s eyes flashed.”

21

Preparing For Deliverance

Perhaps, as you have been reading, you have recognised that there are demons at work within you. You did not previously understand the pressures you were enduring, but now you have been able to identify them. Thank God! You no longer need to endure those pressures passively.

In this chapter I will show you the way that leads to deliverance and to victory. The wonderful secret is this: You do not have to win the victory for yourself. You can enter into the victory that Jesus, by His death and resurrection, has already won for you.

On the cross Jesus paid the full and final penalty for all the sins of all people of every age and of every race. He was the Lamb of God who carried away the sin of the world (see John 1:29). By raising Him from the dead, God demonstrated to the universe that His justice was fully and finally satisfied by the propitiation Jesus had made for our sins.

The sacrifice of Jesus on your behalf is the one all-sufficient basis on which you can claim a full release from every demonic force Satan has directed against you. Once you realise this and act in faith on it, you will be able to say with Paul, “But thanks be to God, who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ” (1 Corinthians 15:57).

If you decide to claim the deliverance God has provided for you, you have two options: to seek ministry from your pastor or fellow Christians, or to turn directly to the Lord for the help you need.

If you have access to a church or other ministry willing to help you, then by all means seek their help. It is important to make sure, however, that they are sincere, Bible-believing Christians and that they understand what is involved in dealing with demons. If you, as a Christian, approach them and discover that they do not believe a Christian can have a demon, then obviously they will not be able to help you.

In our U.S. office we receive letters regularly from people who have come to realise they need deliverance from demons and are asking us to recommend some church or ministry in their area that will help them. Regrettably, more often than not, we do not know anyone to whom we can conscientiously direct them. It reminds me of a scene in the ministry of Jesus:

But when He saw the multitudes, He was moved with compassion for them, because they were weary and scattered, like sheep having no shepherd. Then He said to His disciples, “The harvest truly is plentiful, but the labourers are few. Therefore pray the Lord of the harvest to send out labourers into His harvest.”

Matthew 9:36-37

The ministry of deliverance is a harvest field in which many properly equipped workers are needed. I realise, therefore, that many who read this book may not have any human source of help to whom they can turn. But thanks be to God, the way is always open to the One who is the Deliverer – Jesus! If you decide to take this route, I have outlined for you a series of nine steps that can lead you through to the deliverance and victory you need:

Step No. 1: Personally affirm your faith in Christ

Step No. 2: Humble yourself

Step No. 3: Confess any known sin

Step No. 4: Repent of all sins

Step No. 5: Forgive all other people

Step No. 6: Break with the occult and all false religion

Step No. 7: Prepare to be released from every curse over your life

Step No. 8: Take your stand with God

Step No. 9: Expel!

First, however, it is important to make sure of your personal relationship with God. If you do not already know you are a born-again child of God, with all your sins forgiven through Jesus’ sacrifice, then you can, by the very act of following these steps, enter into a direct, personal relationship with God as your Father. If, on the other hand, you already have a personal relationship with God, going through these steps will strengthen your faith and give you a solid, scriptural basis on which to seek the help that you need from Him.

Read carefully through the nine steps in this chapter, step by step, until you are sure you fully understand each of them. Then, in chapter 22, I will provide you with a form of prayer by which you can claim your deliverance from every demonic oppression. You are protected by the blood of Jesus, as I said in chapter 16, only when you are rightly related to Him and walking in obedience. Be sure, therefore, that you have prayed the prayer in faith before you take your stand against the demons.

Step No. 1: Personally Affirm Your Faith in Christ

Jesus is the “High Priest of our confession” (Hebrews 3:1). The Greek word translated confession means “saying the same as. . . .” Therefore, we say the same about what Jesus has done for us as the Bible has already said. We make the words of our mouths agree with the Word of God. We proclaim the victory of Jesus in a bold and personal way on our own behalf. When we do so, we invoke His ministry as our High Priest to bring our need before God the Father, thus releasing the whole authority of heaven on our behalf.

If we fail to confess our faith in this way, we give Jesus no basis on which to intervene for us.

Step No. 2: Humble Yourself

“God resists the proud,
but gives grace to the humble.”
Therefore humble yourselves under
the mighty hand of God. . . .

1 Peter 5:5-6, emphasis added

If we approach God with an attitude of pride, He resists us and we have no access to Him. So our first step toward God must be to humble ourselves, to say to God, “I need you!”

God never offers to make us humble. Throughout the Bible He places the responsibility on us. God can humiliate us, and sometimes He may have to; but only we can make ourselves humble. If we are willing, however, God will supply all the grace we need.

When we seek deliverance from demons, there may come a point when we have to choose between dignity and deliverance. If dignity becomes more important than deliverance, we have not really repented of our pride.

I was approached once by a doctor’s wife in the Deep South of the U.S. – an old-style, genteel lady who said, “Mr. Prince, if I understand you rightly, when I seek deliverance the way you describe it, I may end up screaming.”

“It could happen,” I replied.

“But I was brought up that a lady doesn’t scream in public.”

“Well,” I said, “suppose you were in a river drowning, about to go down for the third time, and you thought there might be somebody on the bank who could rescue you. Would you be too ladylike to scream?”

I needed to say no more.

If you are not prepared to humble yourself, you will not be willing to take the steps that follow.

Step No. 3: Confess Any Known Sin

Nowhere in the Bible does God commit Himself to forgive sins that have not been confessed. But for those who confess, His promise is clear: “If we confess our sins, He is faithful and just to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness” (1 John 1:9). God is faithful because He has promised. He is just because Jesus has already paid the penalty for our sins.

If you are troubled about some specific sin, be honest about it. Do not call it by some fancy psychiatric name. Most of the names for our basic sins are not pretty. And God forgives them only when we acknowledge them as sins. He never promises to forgive “problems.” If you have a “problem” with overeating, call it by its name: the sin of gluttony. If it is lust, call it lust. If it is hatred, call it hatred. If it is gossip, call it gossip.

Remember, too, that once you have told God the worst about yourself, you have not shocked Him. He knew it all before you told Him. Furthermore, He still loves you!

I referred in chapter 13 to God’s warning that He visits the sins of the fathers on their children to the third and fourth generations (see Exodus 20:3-5). This may apply in your case. The sins of your ancestors do not make you guilty, but they can be causing you to suffer from their consequences. It may be advisable for you to confess and disassociate yourself from any sins that your ancestors committed. This applies particularly to the occult or a false religion.

It is not wise, however, to indulge in self-analysis. Simply relax and let the Holy Spirit bring to your mind any specific sins you need to confess. Remember, He is your Helper.

Step No. 4: Repent of All Sins

It is necessary to confess your sins, but that by itself is not enough. You must also repent for your sins. “He who covers his sins will not prosper, but whoever confesses and forsakes them will have mercy” (Proverbs 28:13). You must first confess, then forsake your sins. To forsake your sins means to turn away from them completely.

A young man said to me once, “I think I have a spirit of lust, but I rather enjoy it. Do you think God will deliver me from it?”

“Definitely not!” I replied. “God delivers us from our enemies, not from our friends. But if you will make your friend your enemy, then you can ask God to deliver you. You need to ask Him to help you hate that sin as He hates it.”

Repentance involves two things. First you must accept personal responsibility for what you have done. You cannot hide behind some other person – a parent, spouse or minister, perhaps – and hold him or her responsible for the wrong things you yourself have done. Nor can you blame demons for your sin. Your attitude must be: I am guilty, and I acknowledge it.

Second, you must take the same stand against your sin that God Himself takes. Do not try in any way to minimise or excuse it. Hate it as God hates it! Then sin will have no more power over you.

Step No. 5: Forgive All Other People

In Mark 11:25-26 Jesus established an unvarying spiritual law:

“And whenever you stand praying, if you have anything against anyone, forgive him, that your Father in heaven may also forgive you your trespasses. But if you do not forgive, neither will your Father in heaven forgive your trespasses.”

If we desire forgiveness from God for our sins, we must unconditionally forgive all those who have sinned against us.

In chapter 18 I mentioned the parable Jesus told about a servant whose master forgave him a debt equivalent to several million dollars, yet he himself refused to forgive his fellow servant a debt of just a few dollars (see Matthew 18:23-35). When we consider the incalculable debt each of us owes God for the sins we have committed against Him, the most that any fellow human being owes us is, by comparison, just a few dollars.

The judgement on the unforgiving servant was to be delivered “to the torturers” (verse 34). In chapter 18 I compared the activity of demons to that of the torturers. If you want to be delivered from the torturers, you must freely forgive all those who have offended or harmed you in any way.

Remember that forgiving another person is not primarily an emotion. It is a decision of the will. First you must make a firm decision. Then you must verbalise it: “I forgive So-and-so of all the wrong he [or she] did to me. I lay down all bitterness, all resentment, all hatred.”

Deciding in your heart, then speaking it out with your mouth, makes your act of forgiving effective.

Step No. 6: Break with the Occult and All False Religion

I explained in chapter 14 how intensely God hates any doctrine or practice that puts some other person or thing in the place of undivided loyalty and wholehearted worship that belongs solely to God. Somewhere in the background of all these other systems lurks the one who is the archenemy of God and man. If you want to draw near to God, you must sever all contact with Satan.

This includes removing from your possession, and from where you live, anything that in any way links you to the occult or to the satanic. This includes books, souvenirs, charms and objects of art. Remember Moses’ warning to Israel: “Nor shall you bring an abomination into your house, lest you be doomed to destruction like it. . .” (Deuteronomy 7:26).

The best way to dispose of such things is, if possible, to burn them. Remember, this is how the Christians in Ephesus responded when they realised their occult scrolls linked them to the power of demons. Follow their example!

If your circumstances prevent you from doing this immediately, make a commitment to God to do it just as soon as you have the opportunity.

Step No. 7: Prepare to Be Released from Every Curse over Your Life

The Bible has much to say about the power of blessings and curses. Altogether it mentions them about six hundred times. Contemporary Western Christendom has tended to focus on the blessings and to regard the curses as a superstitious carryover from the Middle Ages. But this is unscriptural and unrealistic.

I have compared a curse to a dark shadow over our lives that shuts out part (at least) of God’s blessings. Two of the blessings that may be excluded by a curse are physical healing and deliverance from evil spirits.

Over the years I have compiled a list of some problems that commonly indicate that a curse is at work:

Mental or emotional breakdown
Repeated or chronic sicknesses (especially if hereditary)
Barrenness, a tendency to miscarry or related female problems
Breakdown of marriage and family alienation
Continuing financial insufficiency
Being “accident-prone”
A family history of suicides or unnatural or untimely deaths

There is, as I have said, one all-sufficient scriptural basis for release from a curse: the sacrifice of Jesus on the cross by which He took on Himself every curse due to us, that in return we might inherit the blessings of Abraham, who was blessed by God in all things (see Genesis 24:1; Galatians 3:13-14). (For further instruction, refer to my book Blessing or Curse: You Can Choose!)

If you sense there is some curse over your life, seek release from it on the basis of what Jesus did for you on the cross when He was made a curse. (I will give you the words to pray in the next chapter.)

Step No. 8: Take Your Stand with God

Make a firm decision and speak it out: “I submit my will, my purpose, my future, my whole life to God. I take my stand with God against all sin, all evil and every kind of demon.”

As soon as you take your stand with God, He also takes His stand with you. You can enjoy the confidence expressed in Romans 8:31: “If God is for us, who can be against us?”

One way God may come to your help is by revealing the identity of any demons you need to expel.

I commented in chapter 8 that dealing with a demon can be like dealing with a fierce dog. When you call the dog by its name, you have more authority over it. You may already be aware of the names of a specific demon or demons from which you need to be delivered. Or it may happen that as you enter the process of deliverance, a name of a demon will come to your mind. These are two of the ways the Holy Spirit may come to your help.

At the end of one deliverance service, a young man asked me, “Is there such a thing as a spirit of tooth decay?”

“I’ve never heard of such a spirit,” I replied, “but if the Holy Spirit says there is one, then there is.”

“Well, that’s what I’ve just been delivered from,” the young man told me.

Many years later the same man, no longer young, told me the result of that deliverance.

“I would go to the dentist and have a tooth filled,” he said, “but after a year or two, the tooth would decay beneath the filling and I would need a new filling. But since I was delivered from the spirit of tooth decay, I’ve never had that problem again.”

If the Holy Spirit does give you the name of a specific demon, your next step must be to take a deliberate stand with God against the demon, and to verbalise it. Speak it out: “You spirit of lust [or rejection or confusion or whatever], I take my stand against you in the name of Jesus. I no longer submit to you. You have no more place in me. I command you to go!”

You cannot afford to be passive. Remember James 4:7: “Submit to God. Resist the devil and he will flee from you.”

Step No. 9: Expel!

This is so simple and practical that it does not seem spiritual. But it works! You should not attempt to do it, however, until you have prayed the prayer in the next chapter.

I explained in chapter 11 that the word for spirit in both Hebrew and Greek is the word for wind – and also the word for breath. So how do you get rid of breath? You expel it, usually through your mouth.

There are, however, eight other orifices in the human body. At times a demon may come out through any one of them, or in other ways. In chapter 19 I related the story of the student Christopher and how a demon of doubt came out through his left ear. I have also mentioned that a demon of masturbation frequently comes out through the fingers. A spirit of crippling is often expelled with convulsive movements of the body.

If it happens that a demon does not come out through your mouth, but through some other orifice or area of your body, you will become aware of it. Co-operate with the Holy Spirit and He will show you what to do. But most frequently you may expect to expel a demon through your mouth.

A mother came to me once with her little boy of about four and asked me to pray for him.

“What’s his problem?” I asked.

“Allergies.”

“What kind of allergies?”

“Food allergies.”

“What kinds of food is he allergic to?”

“Tell me what he isn’t allergic to!”

Then I told the mother, “I’m going to deal with this as an evil spirit. Is that all right?”

She gave her consent.

Then I turned to the little boy and explained, “There’s a bad spirit in you, like a breath, and it keeps you from eating the things you like. I’m going to command it to come out of you, and when I say, ‘In the name of Jesus,’ I want you to blow it out. O.K.?”

The boy nodded, and behaved like a well-trained little soldier. I commanded the evil spirit to leave him, and when I said, “In the name of Jesus!” the boy blew out four times. Nothing further happened. No emotion, no excitement. I wondered whether the boy had really been delivered, but I had to leave it with the Lord.

Three days later the mother came back and asked for prayer for herself.

“What’s your problem?” I asked.

“Allergies,” she replied.

“Tell me first what happened to your son,” I said.

“He came home with me,” she said, “marched straight up to the refrigerator and sampled everything in it – and nothing did him any harm!”

I remembered what Jesus said about the need to become like little children.

After you have said your prayer for deliverance and concluded with “Amen!” begin to expel. That is a decision of your will, followed by an action of your muscles.

At the same time, make way for the demon or demons to come out. Keep the exit clear! Do not go on praying or start to speak in tongues. I have discovered that movement of the lips and tongue in speech acts as a barrier to keep the demon in. Think of an ambulance coming down the road, lights flashing and siren blaring. All other traffic moves off to the side of the road. Do the same in your throat. Clear the way for the demon to come out.

As you begin to expel, what comes out first may be just natural human breath. But after a short while, something other than human breath will start coming out. That is your enemy! Keep the pressure on!

There may be different manifestations as a demon emerges. It may be scarcely perceptible, just a little sigh or yawn. Or it may come with sobbing, groaning, coughing, screaming or roaring. Remember, in the ministry of Philip, the demons came out with loud cries. One woman delivered from a demon of nicotine yawned so widely that she thought she was going to dislocate her jaw! But when she closed her mouth, she was free from nicotine.

Set no predetermined limit as to how long you will go on expelling. Keep on as long as there are any demons to come out.

When a demon is coming out, some people – usually women – may go on screaming without receiving any release. This indicates that the demon has stopped in the narrow section of the throat and is holding on there to avoid being expelled. In such cases, a deliberate, forceful cough will usually dislodge the demon and force it out. In a deliverance service, sometimes a demon’s screaming will distract others seeking deliverance, hindering them and even making them afraid. This is when workers need to act quickly and help the person screaming to get released.

Many different things may happen when a demon comes out. But remember, when you speak in the name of Jesus, you have authority over the demons. Do not yield to a spirit of fear. Remember, too, that the Holy Spirit is there with you to help you. Yield fully to Him and let Him guide you through to full victory!

Now on to the prayer.

Part 3

Seven Questions

The subject of demons, as I pointed out in the introduction to this book, has often been surrounded with superstitious dread. Christians have sometimes had the attitude that “if I leave demons alone, they will leave me alone.” Regrettably, that is not true. Demons will not leave you alone. The fact that you are a Christian does not in itself protect you. On the contrary, demons view Christians as their primary target for attack.

Your best protection, therefore, is to discover what Scripture reveals about the nature and activity of demons. Then you will be able to avail yourself of the protection God has provided for you through faith in Christ.

I have found there are certain questions concerning the realm of the demonic that people frequently ask. In this section I consider seven such questions:

What are demons?
Flesh or demons?
How do demons come in?
What is the occult?
Is witchcraft still at work today?
Do Christians ever need deliverance from demons?
Will the Holy Spirit indwell an unclean vessel?

To each question I offer an answer based on Scripture and on my personal observation and experience over many years. These will help clear up many common misunderstandings and will prepare you for Part 4, in which you will actually come to grips with demons. At the end of chapters 14, 16 and 17, you will find personal testimonies of Christians who relate their experiences with demons.